<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The tythe-takers cart overthrown or, The downfall of tythes. Proved that they are not to be payd now, either to the appropriate or impropriate parsons or persons. Pen'd for the general satisfaction and easement of all the people of England. By D. Lupton, servant of Christ Jesus in the work of the Gospel.</title>
            <author>Lupton, Donald, d. 1676.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88653</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3495</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1380_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209388</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868268</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868268</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169894</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88653)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169894)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 180:E1380[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The tythe-takers cart overthrown or, The downfall of tythes. Proved that they are not to be payd now, either to the appropriate or impropriate parsons or persons. Pen'd for the general satisfaction and easement of all the people of England. By D. Lupton, servant of Christ Jesus in the work of the Gospel.</title>
                  <author>Lupton, Donald, d. 1676.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>54, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.M. for R. Harford, at the Bible and States arms in Little Brirain [sic],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first and last leaves are blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 27 1651"; the '2' in the imprint has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tithes --  Great Britain --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169894:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Tythe-Takers Cart. Overthrown.</p>
            <p>OR, THE DOWNFALL OF TYTHES.</p>
            <p>Proved that they are not to be payd now, either to the <hi>Appropriate</hi> or <hi>Jmpropriate</hi> Parſons or Perſons.</p>
            <p>Pen'd for the General Satisfaction and Eaſement of all the People of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By D. LUPTON, Servant of Chriſt Jeſus in the Work of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <p>They all look to their own way, every one for his gain from his quarter.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ISAI. 56.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for <hi>R. Harford</hi> at the Bible and States arms in Little Britain. 1652</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:169894:2"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:169894:2"/>
            <head>THE Tythe-Takers Cart Overthrown.</head>
            <p>MAnifold have been the Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (and not without juſt cauſe) for the putting down and taking away of Tythes, and ſome men have already ſet forth their Judgment in print againſt them; ſo that (methinks) I hear theſe Corn-takers bewail their unſtable condition, and to cry out, as once the Silver-Smiths did at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> that <hi>this their Craft is in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169894:3"/>danger to come to nought;</hi> and indeed they may more earneſtly lament, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by <hi>this Craft they have their wealth;</hi> and to loſe their beloved adored Silver <hi>Diana,</hi> their Wealth, this cuts deep. Now there be two ſorts of people who both ſtiffly pretend a right unto Tythes, <hi>viz.</hi> the Appropriate and the Impropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Parſons and Perſons. The firſt of theſe will perſwade men (if they pleaſe to believe them) that they are true Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites, and that they have their right even from <hi>Melchizedec,</hi> or at leaſt can prove their title from <hi>Aaron;</hi> and to ſpeak truth, they ſavour a little too much of the Jewiſh Condition and Profeſſion; and theſe have (partly by peoples igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and partly by their falſe alledging of Scriptures, with the ſtrength of ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Authority hitherto for confirmation of their demands) forc'd a conceit in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mens opinions (nay and Conſciences too) that it is a damnable ſin to refuſe to pay Tythes.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort which are the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriators of whom we may ſay juſtly,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169894:3"/>that <hi>they are known to be hard men, reaping where they have not ſown, and gathering where they have not ſtrawed, Mat.</hi> 25.24. And theſe challenge a Right alſo unto Tythes, partly by Royal Donation, partly by a long continued Purchaſe, ever ſince <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth diſſolved the Abbies and Monaſteries, who either gave them to ſuch as firſt beg'd them, or bought them at his and Courtiers hands: ſo theſe hold all to be their own which was by Prerogative given them, or what they or their Anceſtors eaſily purchaſed or layd hands on; and hereupon theſe as eagerly as the other preſs and oppreſs the poor Commons of this Nation for the payment of Tythes, and do run to and fro, and grudg if they be not ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, or if they get not what they come for; and this Trade they have long ſet up, and grown fat and rich by it alſo, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt without controul: But now of late mens wits and wills are both ſet againſt them, people begin to grow wiſer, by paying too dear for their own goods and hard labours, and thouſands of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169894:4"/>ſolid, and well-affected Subjects of this Land are reſolved (and have good hopes to ſee them effected) to do their beſt to remove this Antiquated Jewiſh or Popiſh Relique (for better it is not) clear out of this Nation. To the help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forward of whoſe deſires and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, this Subject took courage to give both Appropriate and Impropriate a <hi>Memento,</hi> and a little to try &amp; queſtion their proceedings, and to ſhew to all men upon what a weak and ſandy foundation their long and ſeemingly ſtrong Tythe-taking hath been erected and upheld: We intend to handle both theſe ſorts, as well the <hi>Appropriating Tyther,</hi> as the <hi>Impropriate:</hi> And becauſe the firſt of theſe ſtands like another <hi>Goliah,</hi> and ſcorns and bids defiance to all Encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and hopes that <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, the Canon Law, Civil Law and common Law, the Caſuiſts and School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, will all warrant them to take Tythes without doubt or ſcruple; we will therefore firſt ſay unto them,
<list>
                  <item>1. That the pretending Levites,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169894:4"/>Prieſts, Presbyters, or Miniſters, have not any juſt claim or right unto Tythes.</item>
                  <item>2. That Tythes (though they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive themſelves lawfully called, and ſent into their Function) are not now <hi>(in genere ſuo)</hi> in that kind to be paid or demanded.</item>
                  <item>3. That ſundry and manifold are the Evils, Abuſes and Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies by paying Tythes.</item>
                  <item>4. Miniſters in other Reformed places have none, nor did Chriſt or his Apoſtles demand any.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>For to begin with the firſt, 'tis known, <hi>Poſito fundamento ponitur fundatum, &amp; ſublato tollitur;</hi> the Foundation is all in all, no building without it either ſafe or comely: We call them <hi>pretending Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> and Presbyters, becauſe they ſeem, and are not: Therefore ſeeing they glory much, and hold all their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to Tythes, <hi>quatenùs tales,</hi> (i.e.) as ſuch men, as Miniſters of Chriſt and his Goſpel, we demand therefore of them,</p>
            <p>That before they take mens Corn and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169894:5"/>Goods, &amp;c. under that notion and term of Tythes, due to them by vertue of their Calling, whether or no it be not juſt and fitting, that they firſt prove themſelves the men lawfully called and lawfully ſent unto, and into that Office and Employment, that there may be no miſtake of the perſon, for the miſtaking in this is the miſcarriage of all: We doubt that all theſe who ſo receive Tythes, are not the Servants of Chriſt: We know, that though a debt be due to be paid to another, yet he that pays it will be ſure that he pays it to that man only who hath a ſole, proper, and juſt right unto it, and in it. Now in this caſe, though Parſons lay claim to Tythes as a due to them as, they ſay, they are Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, yet the doubt and queſtion ſtill is, whether they be the Miniſters of Chriſt, or not?</p>
            <p>And we do deſire them not to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended that this ſcrutiny is made, ſeeing they are bound to ſatisfie the weaker Conſciences in any ſcruple they can, and therefore ſpecially in this; for if they be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169894:5"/>not ſuch men as they profeſs, 'tis not fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they ſhould longer deceive men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſuch a pretence, and ſo render them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves obnoxious to ſcandal, if they make not this firſt doubt free from doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. 'Twas a queſtion put to <hi>John Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt</hi> almoſt to this purpoſe, <hi>Who art thou?</hi> Now he did not deny to give a ſpeedy anſwer, <hi>I am not the Chriſt;</hi> and ſo upon further demands gave further ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by not aſſuming to himſelf either a falſe Office or a feigned Perſon, but ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted from the Word of God who indeed he was, and to what Office he was by Divine Deſignation layd out for. We deſire theſe Parſons to take ſome pains to vindicate their Authority and Office alſo (if they can) from Gods Word; 'twill make men a great deal the more willing to allow them a liberal Maintenance, were they throughly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied who put them upon this Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and by what Authority they do theſe things; for either they aſſume it to themſelves, or elſe 'tis given; if the firſt of theſe, then 'tis Arrogancy, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169894:6"/>and unlawful, <hi>No man takes this honor unto himſelf,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.4. If the ſecond, then by whom? If only from other men, and corrupt too, then, as our Saviour ſpeaks it, <hi>how can ye believe who receive honour one of another, Joh.</hi> 5.44. If from Chriſt, and his bleſſed Spirit of Truth, and the Apoſtles, they themſelves plead not their Viſible Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Presbytery, or Ordination of Miniſters, ſo high as from the two firſt: but from the Apoſtles times, by the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of hands of the Presbytery from <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> and other Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, they hold out, and make the World believe, their perpetuated Viſibility and Ordination of Miniſters, made from time to time, and ſo even to this time, by one another. And by this Rule their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination came in corrupted times and by corrupted perſons into the hands of the Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> which Gangrene ſpread it ſelf by the Popes policy into all Kingdoms, for the Kingdoms of the World have been made drunk with her fornications; and ſo the Popes Doctrine
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169894:6"/>and Diſcipline advanc'd it ſelf into our Nation, and ſo our Archbiſhops and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and other Miniſters, had Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by the Popes Power and Keys, and theſe from them. Behold we pray you all good people of <hi>England,</hi> the Claim and Title our pretending Presbyters lay hold on to prove themſelves lawful Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt, and ſo cry out, that Tythes, all Tythes, are due to them, as ſuch Miniſters and Presbyters. Now that their Claim to Tythes may be of no force or virtue, we ſhall lay down ſome Concluſions againſt their Calling, which being found true and undeniable, they cannot have the face to lay claim any longer, or to take and rake that which is not their own.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt, Therefore we ſay, That their Ordination it ſelf by a viſible deſcent and grant from one to another, is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and againſt divine Truth. How can a clean thing come out of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean? or a ſtreight from a crooked? A corrupted Fountain cannot ſend forth pure ſtreams, nor a rotten Root ſound
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169894:7"/>Branches. Theſe Parſons come out of the loyns of the Biſhops, and they from the Popes Authority; theſe men them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were the pullers down of the Biſhops Power as Antichriſtian, which had they been lawful, why rejected? if unlawful, how can our Presbyters be good who proceed from them? And then,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, Their Ordination of one another as they ſay from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles times, holds up a Viſibility of the Miniſtry, and by conſequence a Viſible Church too, which is not only Popiſh, but oppoſes Chriſts Spiritual Kingdom; <hi>My Kingdom is not of this World:</hi> And we believe the Communion of Saints now. <hi>Faith,</hi> ſays the Apoſtle, <hi>is of things not ſeen,</hi> Heb. 11.1. He himſelf is called <hi>the King Inviſible,</hi> his Kingdom, his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, his Ordinances and People are all Spiritual and Inviſible, and Godlineſs it ſelf is called <hi>a great Myſtery,</hi> and yet our Presbyters and pretending Miniſters will be viſible and worldly; how can light and darkneſs agree? But,</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:169894:7"/>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, The Prophets of God were called by God, and extraordinarily endowed, not with titles only, but with gifts and graces, and ſent immediately; Behold, <hi>I ſend THEE, even THEE, to the houſe of Iſrael,</hi> ſays God unto the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> Ezek. 2. And after them the Apoſtles were all called, and then ſent by Chriſt; <hi>Behold, I ſend you as ſheep among Wolves:</hi> But are our Presbyters thus called or ſent, or are they ſent at all? Nay, they ſeek places, deſire places, ſolicit for Preferments, do all they can to procure fat Livings, and the beſt Benefices; Do not theſe run, (think you) and God ſends them not? Yea, they climb by Craft and Ambition, and come not in at the door, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. We may know who they are, and to whom they do belong. And yet further,</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, Their works and fruits ſhew they are not of this flock or fold; if they be lawfully ſent, <hi>let them ſhew forth the works of him that ſent them;</hi> the tree is known by his fruits: Can we find in theſe men, though they ſo much cry
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169894:8"/>up Reformation, any true Reformation at all? Oh could we but with Lanthorn and Candle find an Humble Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Miniſter, a merciful One, a liberal-minded One, a meek One, endued with the Spirit of Love, and but even Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Civil Magiſtrate! But alas! the Pulpits are filled, and the Commonwealth too, with ambitious and proud Parſons, with covetous and contentious, ſeeking not, as the Apoſtle ſays, you, but yours, your Goods, your Tythes, not wearing Chriſts Motto, <hi>Hereby ye ſhall be known to be my Diſciples, if ye love one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</hi> We appeal to all <hi>England,</hi> and further too, to their own Conſciences, if this be not ſo: We may ſay then and conclude with the Apoſtle, <hi>Are ye not carnal?</hi> Are not theſe men in their ſins? And then how can we imagine and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude theſe men to be not only Follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but true Teachers of Gods Word alſo, whoſe Actions are diametrically oppoſite unto thoſe of Chriſt? 'Tis ſaid of him, <hi>Behold the Lamb of God, who taketh away the ſins of the world,</hi> Joh. 1. Is he a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169894:8"/>Lamb, and muſt theſe be Lions? Did he take away ſin, and ſhall theſe keep it, and live in it? Oh 'tis time to diſtinguiſh them; they have wore their hoods and vails long enough, it's time to unmask them. We proceed on, and ſay,</p>
            <p n="5">5. Fifthly, Theſe Presbyterian Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters confeſs ſo much themſelves, That there is a twofold Calling to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, one Immediate, another Mediate: now ſay they, the Prophets and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were indeed called Immediately, but they only Mediately: what have they then (we pray you) but what any man might have had for money as well as themſelves? And what is this their Mediate Calling (for more they dare not ſay in truth they have) but an Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Art, as a ſhadow to a body, or as ſign to the thing it ſelf, nothing worth without the Inward? Or have theſe men the Influences and Aſſiſtance of Gods holy Spirit more in them then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers? Or is it promiſed or given to them more then to others who have not that outward Calling? As for their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169894:9"/>parts and Arts, their ſeeming gifts and ſhifts too, they are by ſtudy and other helps acquired, their degrees in Schools humane, not divine: Now this is no ſafe Concluſion, but rather indeed a meer Deluſion, to ſay, becauſe ſuch and ſuch are Miniſters in Arts in a Univerſity, and have ſome knowledg in <hi>Hebrew, Greek,</hi> and <hi>Latin,</hi> and have by Friends and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys too, if not by making Feaſts or Banquets for ſome of the Claſſical Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies, that therefore if ſome of theſe ſhall lay hands upon them, that therefore they are true Miniſters of Chriſt, and from that time forward chiefly, if not ſolely, they may ſet their heart and affections to try all ways poſſible to enjoy a good Parſonage, and then demand and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand Tythes, as true Orothodox and godly Miniſters of Chriſt. Oh falſhood! Oh theſe men to be layd in the ballance will be found too light: And for all this it may yet be asked them, <hi>Friend, how came you in hither, not having on the wedding garment of faithful Labourers in Chriſts Harveſt?</hi> Theſe are the things
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169894:9"/>we put to our Appropriate Parſons, and many more might be added; but we deſire them ſeriouſly upon cold blood, without ſpleen or anger, to ſit down and think upon theſe arguments, and not to blind the Farmers and Husbandmen any longer with comparing themſelves with, and ſtiling themſelves (if we would any longer believe them) in their Panygy-rick Sermons, the Embaſſadors of Chriſt, Watchful Shepherds over the Flock, Stewards of the Myſteries of Chriſt, Gods Husbandmen, and fellow-Laborers, and fellow-Builders, Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Angels; all which they were, were they but the parties they do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be: And though we know that God hath ſuch and will have ſuch to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh the Myſtical Body of Chriſt, and for the gathering together of his people; for he will not want, he hath hidden ones, and deſpiſed ones, who ſhall confound the wiſe and the learned too, &amp; by the fooliſhneſs (as 'tis adjudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) of their teaching he will finiſh his Work, his great Work: But to aſſume
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169894:10"/>theſe glorious Titles unjuſtly, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out due right, and under theſe to Lord it over Gods people by commanding Tythes, is oppreſſing Ambition, and baſe Hypocriſie. We wiſh them to take heed, that what was contemptuouſly objected to our Saviour, be not, or may not be, truly ſaid unto them; <hi>But as for this man we know not whence he is:</hi> They ſaid they knew it not, for who could <hi>declare his generation?</hi> He was from above, and 'twas their ſhame not to know him: But we know theſe Rabbies long enough, and whence they are too. Look to it well, O ye pretending Prieſts and Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, and take no more Tythes, except you had a juſt title unto them: Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Prophets words, <hi>Wo to him that covets an evil Covetouſneſs to himſelf, to heap together that which is not his.</hi> That is for our firſt Demand, to ſhew their right Calling to the Miniſtry, or elſe for ſhame to leave off that antiquated trade of Tythe-taking any more.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:169894:10"/>
               <head>That Tythes (though by our Miniſters proving themſelves to be true Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers) are not <hi>(in genere ſuo)</hi> in their kind to be payd or demanded.</head>
               <p>Where are we now (good People,) under the Law, or under Grace? Shall we groan ſtill under this burthen, which neither we nor our forefathers were able to bear? The Pope you ſee intended to have his Chaplains better fed then taught: 'Tis no marvel they are ſo will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to uphold him, ſince he allows them ſuch fat and large Revenues: But we pray who pays it but the oppreſſed peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>England?</hi> We ſhall therefore do our utmoſt endeavor to ſet them free at laſt from this grievous yoke under which they are; great hopes there are to ſet this Nation in Freedom, in which (we hope) they will ſtand: we only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend their Freedom in this, the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of Tythes, which indeed are not nor ought to be now payd in their kind either to the Appropriate or Impropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Gatherers. And becauſe our Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may proſper the better, and the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169894:11"/>more ſolidly ſtop the mouths of the Gainſayers, for we know we ſhall not want enough who will grudg and repine at us for this our labour, though juſt in it ſelf, and high time to come to light, and though we ſet it not out to do any man wrong, as God knows our intentions; but if poſſible to convince and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert (though it be hard yet it is not impoſſible ſo to do) thoſe whoſe gains come in this way, from going any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this ſame courſe; and however we ſpeed amongſt men we wil diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge our conſcience towards God: a Truth is not to be conceal'd becauſe of oppoſition, and we are ſure were theſe that take Tyth's in our Caſe, they would be as glad of Freedom as our ſelves, <hi>What ye would that men ſhould do unto you even ſo do unto them, Luk.</hi> 6.31. we wiſh every man to be wel perſwaded in his mind herein, for the Receivers are the moſt guilty, they cannot but know that to take other mens goods in an indirect way, muſt needs be ſinful; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to convince theſe our Tythe-takers
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169894:11"/>that they may lay down and leave this practiſe for time to come, or the acting it ſtill againſt the light of Conſcience and Knowledge, it will heighten and augment their condemnation, we lay down theſe Arguments following to prove our Aſſertion to be juſt, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="arguments">
               <head>That Tythes are not now to be Paid, or Demanded.</head>
               <p>
                  <label>Argum. 1.</label> Firſt, there is a change of that Law by which Tythes were eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed and commanded, and of the Prieſt-hood too; both are changed, both are diſanulled, as we have it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.12. <hi>The Prieſt-hood being changed there is of Neceſsity</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>a change alſo of the Law;</hi> the change of the one of neceſſity brings a change of the other, there is ſuch a Relation betwixt them that the one cannot be or ſtand in force without the other: what a change of the Law? of what Law (we pray) but of the Ceremonial Law, of the Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Law, by virtue whereof the Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Prieſts and Levites did receive Tythes? now that there was ſuch a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169894:12"/>change of the Prieſt-hood appears, for there aroſe <hi>another Prieſt after the Order of Melchizedec,</hi> and not called after the <hi>Order of Aaron, Heb.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 11.15. and therefore ſays of him, <hi>That he was not made after the Law of a carnal Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but after the Power of an endleſs life, Heb.</hi> 7.16. and again he ſaith of Chriſt, <hi>But this man becauſe he continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth for ever, hath an unchangeable Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, v.</hi> 24. But this man, not <hi>Aaron</hi> but Chriſt, by way of diſtinction and excellencie too; and ſpeaking fully in <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 20. of the change, ſayes, even Jeſus, <hi>who is made a Prieſt for ever after the Order of Melchizedec,</hi> and further, <hi>who ſprang out of Judah, and pertained to another Tribe,</hi> v. 13, 14. <hi>Who is an high Prieſt over the Houſe of God,</hi> Heb. 10.21. This being infallibly true, it follows, that the Law is changed alſo: So that if our Miniſters ſhall plead for Tythes from <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> or the old Law, we muſt tell them, that herein they ſhew themſelves to be old Jews, denying that Chriſt is come. Let them conſider it
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169894:12"/>well, for this hath been their ſtrong O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion and Determination, and this they have held out to the people as a ſure de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, when alas 'tis a plain argument a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, but it paſſed for current in times of Ignorance and Popiſh Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition. That's our firſt dart againſt Tythe-takers. But,</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Argum. 2.</label> Secondly, Tythes by the Levitical Law were but carnal Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and but meer ſhadows and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.1. and to laſt only until the <hi>Time of Reformation, Heb.</hi> 9.10. until Chriſt: Now that time being come, and the Reformation in practiſe, ſhall all things, and perſons, and ſervices be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and ſhall we ſtill retain and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold this Antiquated Jewiſh Levitical Ceremonial Relique amongſt us, and rely yet upon meer figures and old vain ſhadows? hold more love to <hi>Aarons</hi> Ordinances, weak and vaniſhing, then we will unto the Commandments of Jeſus Chriſt? Pauſe hereupon we pray you who take Tythes. Yet,</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Argum. 3.</label> Thirdly, That Law of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169894:13"/>Tythes was made only to bind that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Jews, and Gods Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was, that they ſhould be payd to their Levites, <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.10. <hi>I have given thee the tenth, &amp;c.</hi> and the people that failed in the payment of them were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed, even that whole Nation, as we have it, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8, 9, 10. 'Tis true indeed, <hi>That Nation,</hi> but 'tis not ſaid, <hi>All Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:</hi> We are Gentiles, not Jews, not under the Law, but under Grace, not of Jewiſh Extraction, and therefore not ſubject to their Ceremonial Law of Tything: If our Tythe-takers will have Tythes payd them, let them ſhew their Genealogy from <hi>Aarons</hi> Loyns, and produce their Succeſſion legally; and yet if they ſhould, which they cannot perform, we might tell them plainly, We are of another Nation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they demand Tythes of a wrong people. We inſiſt upon this the more ſtrictly, that they may ſee their Error the ſooner, and ſhew by what Law they lay claim to Tythes. Therefore,</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Argum. 4.</label> Fourthly, <hi>Moſes</hi> Law will
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169894:13"/>not defend their Action, for, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, thoſe Ordinances wax old, <hi>I will make</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>a New Covenant,</hi> not like the firſt, which had Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Divine Service, and a worldly Tabernacle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.1. Mark, he ſaith, <hi>a New,</hi> ſo that the firſt is made old, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.13. Now ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>That which decayeth and waxed old</hi> (as the Prieſt-hood and Levitical. Law of Tythes did even in his time) <hi>is ready to vaniſh away, Heb.</hi> 8.13. What was the Law of Sacrifices and Offerings, and of the Jewiſh divine Service and of Tythes (in the Apoſtles time, by the power of Chriſts Doctrine and Spiritual Law) ready to vaniſh away? Was it old, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caying, faulty too? (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks,) for had it been faultleſs, 'twould not have been aboliſhed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.7, 8. And ſhall we of this Nation go ſtill and creep upon old, decaying, Jewiſh props and crutches? And can you who take Tythes by this Levitical Law think any otherwiſe, but that by the Act of this Cuſtom you are faulty, old, decaying,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169894:14"/>and vaniſhing too, and hinder the people of this Land from the Knowledg of Chriſt, by your preaching up Gods Law to <hi>Moſes,</hi> as you pretend, and ſo to your ſelves too for taking of Tythes? and who reſiſts you, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the Ordinance of God. Take heed we ſay, you uphold not that, which Gods Word ſays is old and vaniſhing. Further, to this point we ſay;</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Argum. 5.</label> Fifthly, The Payment of Tythes now, what doth it but keep us under the Law, and ſo hinders us from being Children of Faith, of the Spirit, and of Grace: for as the Apoſtle ſays plainly, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.4. <hi>Who are under the Law, are fallen from Grace:</hi> Now we conceive that the Apoſtle doth not ſo much mean the Moral Law, for that is perpetual and obligatory; but the Ceremonial and Levitical Law, which contained under it the Payment of Tythes. Now there were falſe brethren crept in, who did, amongſt many other Errors, hold up Circumciſion, and other Jewiſh rites
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169894:14"/>and ceremonies; and why not the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Tythes alſo? for they were greedy and covetous in this particular, as we may ſee by that <hi>Wo</hi> which Chriſt denounced unto them for this act, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.42. <hi>Wo unto you Scribes and Phariſees, for ye tythe mint and rue, &amp;c.</hi> they would not loſe the leaſt thing Tythable: even much like our Tythe-maſters, not an Egg or an Apple ſhould eſcape: nay, they uſed rigor and force too; for we read of <hi>Eli's</hi> ſons, that if they ſaw any thing better then other, they would have it, and if the people would not give it them, they would take it by force, <hi>even the beſt, the fat,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.15, 16. <hi>and the beſt of all the Offerings of the children of Iſrael,</hi> verſ. 30. Such are too many of our Rabbies, they will have it, rather then not: ſome have uſed force and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence to the poor of the Land, and too many of them have been and will be their own Carvers; what doth the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding the Ceremonial and Levitical Law debar us from the freedom of Grace, of the ſpirit of Grace, and from
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169894:15"/>Faith: certainly we have good reaſon to abandon and ſhake off ſuch a Jewiſh Schoolmaſter, <hi>Galat.</hi> 3.24. Eſpecially when they would make us to learn ſuch leſſons and laws which <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath freed us from; we wonder how our Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Miniſters can ask Tythes of us, knowing that if they keep and hold that Law, they are fallen from Grace, and are under the curſe; and therefore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that by the Death of our Saviour all that <hi>Moſes</hi> commanded concerning Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal rites and ceremonies had an end (for they were all fulfilled in him,) why is tythe-taking ſo eagerly upheld by theſe men, who pretend to <hi>Chriſts</hi> and not to <hi>Moſes</hi> Law? However, if they ſhal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ſo corrupt for their gains ſake (as who knows not what a ſtrong influence gold and gains have upon corrupted ſpirits?) yet let the godly and ſpiritual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-minded people of our Nation do their utmoſt, not onely to diſcover their deep policy in this particular, but labor alſo to aboliſh and overthrow it; for though <hi>Moſes</hi> was a faithful ſervant, yet
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169894:15"/>
                  <hi>Chriſt is Lord and our God bleſſed for ever.</hi> Yet a ſtep or two further; we proceed, and ſay,</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Argum. 6.</label> Sixthly, That as our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters have held Tythes to be their due <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> and ſo to that purpoſe have quoted divers texts out of <hi>Moſes Plutat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and the Prophets; we reply, That none were to have Tythes ſo but the Jewiſh Levites and their Prieſts: It ſeems then, and concludes ſo too directly, that they are the Prieſts and Levites, or elſe to hold up this their gains would be ſuch; for why Tythes, where there is no Prieſt to ſacrifice, and other Oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? then let's have Circumciſion, and a Tabernacle, an Altar too, or elſe a <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> Temple again erected, and ſo conſequently killing of Bullocks, and Sheep, and Lambs, yes, and Pigeons and turtle Doves alſo. Oh ſee what ill Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences follow in upon the payment of Tythes in this manner. We muſt have an Altar of Incenſe alſo, which will not be a ſweet ſavour in Gods No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils. But what need of theſe, or the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169894:16"/>whole Levitical Law or Prieſthood, ſeeing nor the one, nor the other, nor all the blood of bulls and goats can poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly take away ſins? <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.4. and what is more, the ſame Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>that there is verily a diſanulling of the Commandment going before;</hi> and why ſo? he gives ſufficient reaſons for it, for the weakneſs and unprofitableneſs of it; <hi>for the Law (i. e.)</hi> the Levitical Law, <hi>made nothing perfect, Hebr.</hi> 7.18, 19. So then, if the Levitical Law, nor the Prieſts, could not take away the ſins of the people, but were themſelves ſinful men, and dyed, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.23. and the Law it ſelf weak, unprofitable, imperfect, faulty, old, decaying, and vaniſhing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; and the Oblations termed vain and abominable, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1.11, 12, 13. What faces have our Presbyterian Rabbies to fly unto this for ſhelter and maintenance? for their taking of tythes of the People now in theſe Reformed Times? Well, we hope we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved their old confidence from this Law of demanding tythes. Next in order:</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:169894:16"/>
               <p>
                  <label>Argum. 7.</label> Seventhly, We having them now upon purſuit, let's not leave to follow them a little cloſer; If we will believe them, though they can get little or no comfort from <hi>Moſes</hi> or the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, yet they have other holds, as from the Canon Law, the Civil, the Caſuiſts and Schoolmen: Is't poſſible that theſe men who profeſs Chriſt ſo ſtrictly, and Reformation too, and exclaim againſt the Pope and his Adherents, will yet flee unto <hi>Rome</hi> to a Conclave or Conſiſtory of old muſty and rotten ſuperſtitious Writters, who to uphold their Seat and their State patch up their Tenets with Judaiſm, or the Turkiſh <hi>Alchoran,</hi> who to pleaſe their Father, ſubſcribe all their Judgments to his Verdict, and either will not or dare not print directly what's truth, for fear of his Excommunications and thundering <hi>Anathema's?</hi> But muſt we be kept hoodwink'd ſtill, and muſt be forc'd to have their ſayings obtruded upon us, and pinned upon our ſleeves for truths, though never ſo falſe? Who knows not how they have juggled with
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169894:17"/>the Text it ſelf, terming it <hi>fabula,</hi> a fable? What great Confidence in or from theſe men? What hopes to find truth in the very Chair of lying and ſeducing? What if they ſay Tythes are due <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> and threaten all ſuch with Bell Book and Candle who dare ſpeak or write againſt it, are they therefore ſo? In ſuch a caſe as this is muſt Antichriſt be choſen Judg and Umpire. Oh ye Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of <hi>England,</hi> if yet ye be ſo, may we not tell you herein, as our Saviour told that young man, who ſaid he would follow him whither ſoever he went, <hi>The Foxes have holes, and the birds of the ayr have neſts?</hi> Have you yet lurking holes from the Popiſh Canoniſts, and neſts too amongſt the Popiſh Lawyers? Alas, Prieſts we know have but little skill, and of late as bad ſucceſs, in making and truſting to Canons: It muſt not be the Civilian nor the wrangling ſophiſtating Schoolmen who muſt be Judges in this Point; and therefore knowing and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping you will not foul your mouths with theſe Rabble of Deceivers, we tell
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169894:17"/>you we appeal in this particular to Gods Word, if they ſpeak not <hi>according to that, it is becauſe there is no truth in them, Iſa.</hi> 8. We are not willing to mention this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling Crue and politique Cheaters, who to uphold <hi>Peters</hi> old Chair, and to fill their own bellies and purſes too, will ſay and unſay any thing; yet for concluſion, this point in agitation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us at preſent is yet unheard of and untouch'd amongſt them at <hi>Rome:</hi> We therefore intending to be as brief as may be, go on and ſay,</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Argum. 8.</label> Eightly, There is not one <hi>Iota</hi> or line directly for the payment of Tythes in kind not in all the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. We'l deal plainly with the world, there are ſome which carry a ſhew which we intend to anſwer, becauſe ſome have made uſe of them contrary to the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them that ſpoke them. The firſt is in <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.2, 3, 4. concerning the <hi>Leper,</hi> unto whom Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Go ſhew thy ſelf unto the Prieſt, and offer the gift that Moſes commanded for a Teſtimony unto them.</hi> Some concluding that Chriſt ſtood for
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169894:18"/>payment of Tythes himſelf according to <hi>Moſes</hi> Law; but let's a little examine the matter, and it will make nothing for our Tythe-takers now; for firſt, Chriſt was not then glorified, ſecondly, the Jewiſh Clergy was then in power and being, though miſerably corrupted; and that party who was healed of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo liable to payment, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſts Injunction was both equal and righteous at that time. Another Text too is uſed for payment of Tythes, and that is in thoſe two men who (as our Saviour ſays) <hi>went into the Temple to pray, the one a Phariſee, and the other a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican;</hi> amongſt other particulars which the Phariſee boaſted of, this was one, that he <hi>gave Tythes of all that he poſſeſſed, Luk.</hi> 18.12. See, ſay our Tythe-takers, the very Phariſees did not deny Tythes; and ſo hold out to plain people, that thoſe who deny to pay Tythes are worſe then the Phariſees. We reply, Did he pay Tythes? 'twas his duty to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand then being in force, and he a Jew, and one that pretended to be the ſtricteſt
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169894:18"/>Obſervant of the Law: Now as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Thou that boaſteſt of the Law, through breaking the Law, diſhonoreſt thou God,</hi> Rom. 2.23. It had in him at that time been not only a breach ſimply of the Law, but alſo a diſhonoring God; and yet we have but his own bragging and boaſting word; and ſome ſuſpicion may be moved concerning his doing as he ſaid; for, for all his boaſting, this did not juſtifie; but in the laſt place, this was not a real hiſtory, but a Parable, for the text ſaith, <hi>And he ſpoke this Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Luk.</hi> 18.9. So neither of theſe doth any thing help the cauſe of Tythes at this preſent.</p>
               <p>Well, we come now to the main Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, that large and copious Text of the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7, 8, 9. to 14.) wherein, ſay our Tythe-Takers, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle hath ſufficiently warranted tythes even now under the Goſel: we will take ſome pains therefore about the true opening of this Text: The Apoſtle vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicates indeed his own liberty and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, though he ſays he uſed it not at all,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169894:19"/>
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 15. He ſpeaking of eating and drinking, and leading about a ſiſter, a wife, <hi>verſ.</hi> 4, 5. forbearing to work at his Trade, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. Urgeth his lawfulneſs of doing from three ſimilitudes: 1. from <hi>going to warfare at a mans own charges!</hi> 2. from <hi>planting a vineyard, and not eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the fruit:</hi> 3. from <hi>feeding a flock, and not eating of the milk of the flock,</hi> verſ. 7. Brings an Argument from <hi>Moſes</hi> Law too, from <hi>muzling the ox that treadeth out the corn,</hi> verſ. 9. fetches confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this from plowmen, threſhers, and ſeeds-men, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. proves his doctrine from an Argument called <hi>a Majori ad Minus:</hi> If <hi>we ſow to you ſpiritual, is it a great thing if we ſhall reap your carnal things?</hi> verſ. 11. from the practice of others, <hi>v.</hi> 12. therefore as well to him as to others: proves it alſo from thoſe who miniſtred about holy things in the Temple, and waited at the Altar; both lived of and by it; and ſo concludes this ſubject, that <hi>ſo hath God ordarned, that they who preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel:</hi> an Argument <hi>a pari;</hi> if
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169894:19"/>they lived on that; theſe on this, and this is Gods Ordinance. We have not omitted any thing, we would not will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly in this large Text of Scripture, which ſeems to be the Tythe-Takers ſafeſt and uncontroulable Argument, if it be not throughly examined. But we ſhal make it appear, that this Apoſtle, even in this place, doth not ſo much as mention Tythes; nor can our Miniſters fetch or alledg truly any Authority for their Tythes now from hence. And therefore firſt for his liberty and his plea for maintenance for Preachers: 1. He was an Apoſtle, <hi>Am I not?</hi> verſ. 1. ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies his miſſion; could our men do ſo too? 2. His freedom in preaching, <hi>not chargeable;</hi> Are our Miniſters of this ſtamp? we fear they are not. 3. His priviledg, <hi>ſeen the Lord,</hi> verſ. 1. not onely in ſpirit, but Chriſt appeared to him: Have our Miniſters this ſpiritual happineſs? 4. His effectual operation in their converſion, <hi>v.</hi> 2. O happy man, worthy indeed of allowance, and liberal too! But can ours ſhew their ſeal and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169894:20"/>evidence to mens conſciences, that they have wrought their converſion? we wiſh they could. 5. His confirmation of them in Grace: O where are ſuch Miniſters to be had 6. Eating and drinking; and leading about a ſiſter, a wife; the two firſt things indifferent, and allowed by Chriſt, <hi>Eat and drink ſuch ſuch things as are ſet before you, Luk,</hi> 10.7. <hi>v.</hi> 4, 5. Here's onely meat and drink, an Apoſtles allowance; and yet he had learned to be content and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful too. What will our Presbyters plead to this? whom meat and drink, moneys and all will ſcarce pleaſe? for his lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about a ſiſter, a wife, no ways ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious to ſcandal; a ſiſter by profeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame faith; a wife, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, and as diligent to miniſter to them in their journeying. Divers women of affection to Chriſt, followed him, being ſo taken with his doctrine, <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.2, 3. He was put upon this employment by <hi>Chriſt himſelf,</hi> his warfare, planting and feeding, (<hi>Acts</hi> 22.14, 15.) Ours put themſelves upon it, and thruſt into it for
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169894:20"/>gains and means. Rich Parſonages need not cry out for want of Paſtors; they ſtrive who ſhould get into them firſt. His compariſon from the muzling of the Ox; This creature is laborious, and a pattern of a good Miniſter, <hi>v.</hi> 9. For his Argument from the greater to the leſs, 'twas true, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. He did ſow, <hi>(i. e.)</hi> preach ſpiritual things; Ours too too many of them preach carnal things, as for maintenance by Tythes, nay and contention too, and preach themſelves, and for themſelves, he not. And ſo alſo for his plowing he performed it ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally; ſo of threſhing and ſowing, this was his task; it's good to have a Call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not to run without a Call: and moreover obſerve his labor in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; <hi>I,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>labored more then they all,</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.) A good example to all that undertake this profeſſion, to be true Laborers in Gods Harveſt and Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard: His fetching Authority for Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters means from their practice under the Law, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. for in his time the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> was not quite decayed;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:169894:21"/>The Light of the Goſpel did ſpread, but yet then the Jews Law was not down, it decayed by degrees: but now 'tis no plea for our Miniſters, it being now vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as old, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7. In the laſt place, at <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. from Gods Ordinance we ſay ſo too, 'tis Gods Ordinance, we know, that the Laborer is worthy of his hire: the Apoſtle ſays, they ſhould <hi>live of the Goſpel,</hi> but doth not mention a word to confirm the taking and raking after Tythes: and all this he, good man, did onely perſwade, forc'd it not, rail'd not againſt them, accuſed them not, did not proſecute them at Law, neither did he threaten any of them: And now to ſum up all this, What makes all this for Tythes in kinde? not a word, nor one ſyllable. When we conſider this mans admirable gifts, and his conſtant em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of them; his patience in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and wants too; how he only craves and perſwades, not for any ſuperfluity, but onely to live; what mean and labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious names he takes to himſelf, even of a private Soldier, of a Vine-dreſſer, of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169894:21"/>a Shepherd, of a Plow-man, of a Threſher, and of a Seeds-man, Titles not of honor, but of labor and pains, and all theſe with perſecution too, and onely to live, to preach to live, and live to preach: Look upon this Example O Miniſters, and then bluſh at your Pride, Contention, Debate, Envy, Idleneſs, and Imperiouſneſs: He perſwades, but you'l command; he onely to live of the Goſpel, you to lord it over your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren &amp; the People too; <hi>Ye take too much upon you, ye ſons of Levi, Num.</hi> 16.7, 8. He converted Souls, and confirmed them in the Faith; Oh could you but ſhew ſuch ſeals of your employments! and yet for all this demanded no Tythes at all, onely peoples liberality. We would not, do not, debar a good mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance to you, though you be far inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or to the Apoſtles, onely be not your own Carvers: Allowance we ſay is fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but not in this kind by Tyth-taking. We would not be tedious upon this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, onely give our Miniſters notice that they exact too much upon Gods
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:169894:22"/>people by Tythes. Further, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them in this particular, we ſay,</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Argum. 9.</label> Ninthly, Seeing that <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and the Prophets, nor <hi>Canonists, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vilians, Caſuiſts,</hi> nor <hi>School-men,</hi> nor yet the Word of God in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, will or do uphold them in their practice; they retire to the common Law of the Land, becauſe confirmed by ſeveral Acts of Parliament; and this is it indeed that bolſters them up, and ſwels them ſo, that they think all's their own, and that nothing can hinder them from their Right, as they hold it. Well, Is the whole matter come to this? from <hi>Jure Divino</hi> to <hi>Jure Humano?</hi> Is all their pretences and clamors and buſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings for Tythes all this while ſummed up in this? Tythes are ſetled to our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters by Act of Parliament: This is but a weak plea for them; for we ſay, firſt, what the Parliaments of this Land did in this particular, was out of indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency to encourage them in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, not to heighten them in pride; for Alimony, not for Covetouſneſs;
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169894:22"/>their intentions were honorable, the worſe is the abuſe; but yet thoſe that ſat then, and ruled in chief, had depend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance on the Pope; the Houſes were fill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Popiſh Prelates and Abbots: nay, moſt, if not all in both Houſes, were zealous Papiſts, and had no further knowledg, held it a meritorious Act, and the buſineſs put on by the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and Biſhops of the ſame tribe that the Miniſters were of: and ſo indeed Tythes came in. But we hope many other Acts of Parliament in after times have been repealed; and when it pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth God to ſtir up the ſpirits of this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Parliament to put their Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er into execution in this particular, it may be ſpeedily effected, without either any prejudice to their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, or violation of any mans juſt Right, but to the general and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Freedom of this Nation from Jewiſh and Popiſh Thraldom, for which purpoſe there have been ſundry Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from ſeveral parts and perſons, all deſiring this one thing (as a great grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance)
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169894:23"/>may be taken out of the way: And certainly as 'twas ſaid of <hi>Henry</hi> the eight, that he broke the Popes ſhins when he pull'd down the Abbies and Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries in <hi>England;</hi> ſo it may be ſaid of taking away of Tythes, that being done, he will be cruſh'd to pieces, his bones will be broke, and his body thrown fully from amongſt us in <hi>England.</hi> We pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to another Argument againſt Tythe-paying, and haſten to an end. Therefore,</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Argum. 10.</label> Tenthly, The groſs Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Inconveniences, Troubles, Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, Quarrelings, Contentions, Strifes, Debates, Hatred, Heart-burnings, Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picions, Wrongs, Vexations, Murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Grudgings, and Miſchiefs, which have and do dayly ariſe betwixt the Tythe-takers and the Tythe-payers, as they are not to be numbered, ſo 'tis pity they ſhould not be extinguiſhed, the one think they take too much, the other think they have not enough: What Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, Hamlet, Town or City in all <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which either is not, or hath not been
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:169894:23"/>quarrel'd withall by their wrangling Tything Miniſters? What <hi>Term</hi> hath not been filled with Complaints one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another? What Courts have not, and yet do not even ſwarm with Suits one with another, to the great charges, loſs and vexation of the good people of this Land in travelling and journeying to <hi>London</hi> about Law-ſuits for ſetting out and paying Tythes? How are the Juſtices and Committees toyl'd and wearied at their Meetings and Sittings in hearing Cauſes, one party againſt the other, even with bitterneſs of ſpirit, and all for Tythes? We could weary the Readers, and relate ſuch ſtories of quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels in this kind as are not indeed worth the naming, and yet have been proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with all vehemency and virulency of ſpirit: How can ſuch Miniſters teach the Word of God in meekneſs, who are fill'd with rancor and ill will for want of their due in Tythes, meerly concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo to themſelves, not being ſo in truth? What baſe Informations and Suggeſtions, with indirect Intelligence
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:169894:24"/>too, are brought to their ears, of mens ſtealing, pilfering, and carrying away more then they ſhould, which inflames their ſpirits ſo high and ſo deeply againſt their Neighbors and Pariſhioners, that they are not fully and truly reconciled to them during their whole lives? How are they diſtracted from their Study and ſpiritual Employments? What Weeks and Moneths are wholly conſumed in looking after yours, your Goods, your Tythes, more then after you, and your Souls? How do the hopes of great Tythes render them Mercenary? How do they chop and change their Flocks, as oft as they can by any means procure better and fatter Livings? Oh what true care of Souls can theſe tything Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters have! How can they ſay as <hi>Paul</hi> did, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. <hi>I have coveted no mans ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, nor gold, nor apparel,</hi> or with the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Peter, Silver and gold have I none,</hi> ſince theſe men aym at nothing elſe? Behold the ſpecial fruits of Tything. In the laſt place we ſay,</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Argum. 11.</label> Eleventhly, That all the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:169894:24"/>Reformed Churches beyond the Seas, as thoſe of <hi>Geneva,</hi> of <hi>Baſil,</hi> of <hi>Bern,</hi> of <hi>Zurich,</hi> of <hi>Schafhauſen,</hi> thoſe of <hi>France,</hi> with the Low Countries of <hi>Holland, Zealand,</hi> &amp;c. thoſe likewiſe of <hi>Germany</hi> and of <hi>Denmark</hi> have no Tythes, and yet they live peaceably, quietly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly with and amongſt their people. Our Saviour himſelf when he ſent his Apoſtles to teach the Goſpel, gave not the leaſt direction or precept concerning Tythes; nor did the Primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans demand any: And have our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters any juſter claim or right unto Tythes then any or all theſe think you? Thus much concerning our Appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Tythe-takers, the pretending Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: We come now to the other fort, which are the Impropriate Tythers: Now for certain if theſe who labour in the Word cannot yet ſhew their lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to take Tythes, the other who labor not at all can have nothing to plead for themſelves, yet to convince them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are many who practiſe it, and great ones too, we ſay to them, Firſt,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:169894:25"/> 
                  <label>Argum I. againſt Impropriators.</label>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Their Parſonages were either freely given to them or to their Anceſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors, and therefore may be the freelier ſurrendred again, or elſe eaſily purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, even then for ſo little as is not worth reckoning for now.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They have had a long and a quiet poſſeſſion of them, and in all that time and years have had Tythes payd them without any oppoſition; ſo that long ſince they have not only got in and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered the principal layd out, but have moreover above that procured great E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates and Means to themſelves and heirs for their moneys then disburſed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Their not labouring in teaching the Word, but what is more, their not allowing any Maintenance to Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers (except now of late for fear,) for Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriations of 200 <abbr>
                     <hi>li.</hi>
                  </abbr> 300 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> or 400 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi> per annum,</abbr> have ſinall Vicaridges inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively layd to them, or elſe in policy the Impropriators have themſelves parted with the ſmaller Tythes to a Preacher, either becauſe they are in many places
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169894:25"/>ſcarce worth the labour in gathering, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially with ſo many ill wiſhes of the people who pay them (if not with curſes too,) or elſe becauſe by this Act they take off the peoples hatred from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and transfer it upon the poor Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cars, who muſt either get them in, or ſtarve in their places; and however this Act of theirs doth ſtill and quiet the people, and blind them too, ſo that they ſit down (as yet without complaining againſt their Impropriators, who uſually take Tythes with power, eſpecially if they be (as in many places they are) both Landlord and Parſon too,) for then the poor Tenants dare not reſiſt their Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for fear of being diſmiſt their habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Their Livings were either given to them, or elſe purchaſed from the Crown; and if ſo, reducible whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and to what Uſes ſoever Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in after times ſhal think beſt, they having and alwayes had power, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to call in Crown Lands but alſo to diſpoſe and imploy them, eſpecially in
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:169894:26"/>great abuſes, or publique Exigences and occaſions.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Their purchaſes for the moſt part acted in times of Popery and dark ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition; ſo that in later times many gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen in this Land have in their own conſciences been convicted of their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure, and have laid down of themſelves; ſome others have been perſwaded to part with their Title for a little money by certain Feoffees in and about <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> who did recover ſome of them, and did maintain <hi>Lecturers</hi> and <hi>Schools</hi> with them. Now ſince God hath given more light, let our Gentry and others, who hold ſuch, conſider well of it.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Their Tythe-taking againſt Gods Word: <hi>He that labors not</hi> (ſays the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle) <hi>let him not eat; and he that ſoweth not, why ſhould he reap?</hi> beſides it hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the teaching of Gods Word in ſuch places: for <hi>Impropriations</hi> are common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the greateſt and fatteſt places and pariſhes; and yet hereby theſe Towns are, or have been, deſtitute of Teachers, or elſe they themſelves muſt and have
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:169894:26"/>procured one, and yet payd Tythes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide; for the Vicars (if any be) are kept ſo poor, that they can ſcarce live, though they have labored hardly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly.</p>
               <p>To the <hi>Impropriators,</hi> who have pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed their <hi>Parſonages</hi> of late, we ſay,</p>
               <p n="1">Firſt, 'Twas Covetouſneſs, and hopes of quietneſs of the times, and wealth by their purchaſe, which induced them to buy.</p>
               <p n="2">Secondly, Theſe could not but know that they ventured upon Titles that were hazardable of Tenure, and ſo did or might have precautioned in their bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gains reſtitution of Moneys, if they ſhould be deprvied of them.</p>
               <p n="3">Thirdly, Gave for their purchaſe lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or nothing; ſome perhaps three or four, few not five years purchaſe.</p>
               <p n="4">Fourthly, That Power by which they had them <hi>(viz.)</hi> Kingly Power is now extinguiſhed and aboliſhed; and then how can their Tenures be valid and good?</p>
               <p n="5">Fifthly, Particular Intereſts are not
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:169894:27"/>to be held up againſt a general good, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially when as a conſiderable ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction ſhall be made to the party ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendering, the loſs (if any be proved) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not tota, but partial.</p>
               <p n="6">Sixthly, By their giving up they are ſure to have the peoples love and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, and bleſſing too; whereas the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them may procure, and doth cauſe, the peoples ill-will and hatred, if not curſes too; And 'tis a happineſs they have enjoyed Tythes ſo long without diſturbance, and yet what further is, they may reap benefit and Salvation of their Souls too, by placing an able man to teach Gods Word in ſuch places.</p>
               <p>Theſe are ſome of thoſe many Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, may be uſed to convince as well the one as the other of our Tythe-takers to leave off that trade and courſe. We leave the iſſue to God, and to the pious judgments and diſcretion of our ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Magiſtrates, the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> praying for Gods bleſſings up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their proceedings, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Pag. 17. lin. 19. read <hi>Act</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.31.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>7. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tateuch.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
